export const GOVERNMENTA2021 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. An undesirable attribute of capitalism is mostly seen in __________.",
A: "freedom of choice",
B: "exploitation of labour",
C: "efficient production of goods and services",
D: "effective utilization of labour",
answer: "B. exploitation of labour",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. A constitution that requires an absolute majority of members of parliament to amend is a _________.",
A: "confederal constitution",
B: "federal constitution",
C: "flexible constitution",
D: "rigid constitution",
answer: "D. rigid constitution",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. What is the term given to the action of discontinuing a session of a parliament or other legislative assembly without dissolving?",
A: "Adjournment",
B: "Postponement",
C: "Prorogation",
D: "Recess",
answer: "C. Prorogation",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. In a monocephalous executive system of government, all executive powers are vested in the ________.",
A: "Chief Justice",
B: "President",
C: "Prime Minister",
D: "Speaker",
answer: "B. President",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. The action programme of a political party intended to be carried out when political power is won is known as _________.",
A: "code of conduct",
B: "party constitution",
C: "party survey",
D: "manifesto",
answer: "D. manifesto",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. What does the mass media rely on to gauge public opinion?",
A: "Influential citizens",
B: "Propaganda and interviews",
C: "Polls and surveys",
D: "Rumour and gossip",
answer: "C. Polls and surveys",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. Which of the following options is the role of a newspaper in a state?",
A: "Determines government appointments",
B: "Disseminates information",
C: "Ensures fairness in newspaper circulation",
D: "Ensures fair distribution of relief items",
answer: "B. Disseminates information",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. The Civil Service helps the government to __________.",
A: "recruit personnel for the army",
B: "develop and implement policies effectively",
C: "maintain instability in the state",
D: "stay in power for a long time",
answer: "B. develop and implement policies effectively",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. A citizen is barred from active politics when employed as a __________.",
A: "university lecturer",
B: "priest",
C: "civil servant",
D: "journalist",
answer: "C. civil servant",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. Citizens’ political participation is best practiced under a  _________.",
A: "militant pressure group",
B: "neighbourhood vigilante group",
C: "cooperative society",
D: "political party",
answer: "D. political party",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. The most important function of government is to ensure the ________.",
A: "building of offices and houses",
B: "judiciary is well resourced",
C: "second arm of government is respected",
D: "security of the citizens",
answer: "D. security of the citizens",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. The right to an adequate standard of living falls under _________.",
A: "civil rights",
B: "economic right",
C: "free-market economy",
D: "right to life",
answer: "B. economic right",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. People’s political values are continuously shaped by the following agents except _________.",
A: "education",
B: "family",
C: "media",
D: "ombudsman",
answer: "D. ombudsman",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. In which political system are there two levels of government with considerable devolution?",
A: "Capitalism",
B: "Federalism",
C: "Fascism",
D: "Unitarism",
answer: "B. Federalism",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. A system of government in which people elect their lawmakers and make them accountable for their actions and inactions in government is _________",
A: "a representative government",
B: "first-past-the-post government",
C: "an oligarchy government",
D: "checks and balances system of government",
answer: "A. a representative government",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. Which territories in British West Africa did the colonial government exercise limited jurisdiction?",
A: "Conquered states",
B: "Mandated territories",
C: "Protectorates",
D: "Trust territories",
answer: "C. Protectorates",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. One of the following French West African colonies was the first to gain independence.",
A: "Benin",
B: "Burkina Faso",
C: "Guinea",
D: "Togo",
answer: "C. Guinea",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. The struggle by which the chiefs and people of West Africa fought against political, social, and economic dominance by European powers was referred to as _________.",
A: "imperialism",
B: "nationalism",
C: "neo-colonialism",
D: "liberation",
answer: "B. nationalism",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. The European imperialist penetration into West Africa was primarily motivated by the following considerations except _________.",
A: "compassion",
B: "economic",
C: "social",
D: "military",
answer: "A. compassion",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. Which policy made the colonized French West Africa countries partner with France in her colonial project?",
A: "Assimilation policy",
B: "Association policy",
C: "Indirect rule policy",
D: "Loi Cadre",
answer: "B. Association policy",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. The British colonial governor in West Africa wielded sweeping powers by virtue of ________.",
A: "the land tenure system",
B: "drafting law",
C: "tax collection",
D: "veto power",
answer: "D. veto power",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. The action plan by African countries under the New Partnership for Africa’s Development (NEPAD), aimed at tackling the following issues except _______.",
A: "economic",
B: "political",
C: "religious",
D: "social",
answer: "C. religious",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. What motivated the adoption of Indirect Rule system by the British in her West African colonies?",
A: "Effective and efficient tax system was in place",
B: "Chiefs did not have the power to make laws",
C: "Educated elites were in bed with the British government",
D: "The land was fertile for cash crop farming",
answer: "C. inadequate finance.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. The Economic Community for West African States (ECOWAS) was established primarily to ____________.",
A: "create a common currency for member countries",
B: "prevent neo-colonialism",
C: "sideline French West African countries in economic activities",
D: "Promote economic growth and development among member states",
answer: "D. Promote economic growth and development among member states",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. The media can best contribute to the democratic process of a country by ______.",
A: "lobbying ministers to be in their good books",
B: "setting the agenda for good governance",
C: "inciting strikes and demonstrations",
D: "recounting the achievements of the government in power",
answer: "B. setting the agenda for good governance",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. Public corporations can deliver on their mandate if __________.",
A: "incidence of corruption and mismanagement were dealt with",
B: "loans were secured to pay staff well",
C: "politicians were members of the board",
D: "religious institutions pray for their success",
answer: "A. incidence of corruption and mismanagement were dealt with",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. Citizenship of a state is based on the following requirements except __________.",
A: "birth",
B: "marriage",
C: "education",
D: "naturalization",
answer: "C. education",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. One-party system encourages and often ends up in ________.",
A: "democracy",
B: "dictatorship",
C: "fair electoral contest",
D: "freedom of expression",
answer: "B. dictatorship",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. Which of the following tools is not used by pressure groups to achieve their aim?",
A: "Boycotts",
B: "Demonstrations",
C: "Elections",
D: "Strikes",
answer: "C. Elections",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. Frequent military coup d’états which topple elected governments negatively affect and stall ________.",
A: "education",
B: "culture and religion",
C: "health",
D: "democratic gains",
answer: "D. democratic gains",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. How beneficial is delegated legislation to the democratic process? It __________.",
A: "aids lawmakers to become experts in legislation",
B: "cannot be applied during period of crises",
C: "helps to discipline personnel in the civil service",
D: "permits handling of certain aspects of legislation by non- technocrats",
answer: "A. aids lawmakers to become experts in legislation",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. Local government performs a number of functions on behalf of the central government in the form of ____________.",
A: "employing police officers",
B: "ensuring people attend religious institutions for prayers",
C: "mobilizing of resources for development",
D: "punishing opposition or dissent",
answer: "C. mobilizing of resources for development",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. In an environment of press freedom, the media play the role of ________.",
A: "articulating views of individuals",
B: "inciting people to be lawless",
C: "projecting individuals above the state",
D: "highlighting only the activities of government",
answer: "A. articulating views of individuals",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. Chiefs under the Indirect Rule system were used to carry out unpopular tasks, one of which was ________.",
A: "enforcement of western education",
B: "establishment of churches",
C: "military conscription",
D: "presiding over native courts",
answer: "C. military conscription",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. In restoring peace and security to Liberia and Sierra Leone, the Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS), deployed a military force known as ________.",
A: "Regional Armed Forces (RAF)",
B: "Peace Keeping Force of West Africa (PKFWA)",
C: "ECOWAS Ceasefire Monitoring Group (ECOMOG)",
D: "ECOWAS Heads of State and Government",
answer: "C. ECOWAS Ceasefire Monitoring Group (ECOMOG)",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. The desire for foreign investment and overseas market had become the driving force behind many West African countries’ __________.",
A: "educational policy",
B: "foreign policy",
C: "campaign tool",
D: "dream ideology",
answer: "B. foreign policy",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Citizenship does not only go with rights but also the performance of _________.",
A: "compulsory military service",
B: "compulsory teaching",
C: "certain obligations and duties",
D: "certain religious rites",
answer: "C. certain obligations and duties",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Taking over power, military governments disregard democratic protocols and rule mainly by ___________.",
A: "decree",
B: "popular acclamation",
C: "jury",
D: "court martial",
answer: "A. decree",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. Which electoral system best suits a heterogeneous political environment?",
A: "Non-transferable votes",
B: "Preferential ballot",
C: "Proportional representation",
D: "Run-off election",
answer: "C. Proportional representation",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. Judicial review in a democratic environment is an aspect of _________.",
A: "checks and balances",
B: "a check on the legislature",
C: "a check on the executive and the media",
D: "ensuring the police assist the judiciary in its work",
answer: "A. checks and balances",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. One advantage of multi-party system is that, the _________.",
A: "electorate have wide range of choices",
B: "educated elite represents their people in parliament",
C: "the executive is not restrained by law",
D: "party in power creates employment for all sympathizers",
answer: "A. electorate have wide range of choices",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. The following factors motivated the formation and growth of political parties in British West African territories except _________.",
A: "external socio-political factors",
B: "improvement in communication network",
C: "membership of legislative council",
D: "the role of newspapers",
answer: "A. external socio-political factors",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. Undue political interference in the work of electoral management bodies in West Africa has potential to __________.",
A: "ensure fairness and transparency in their operations",
B: "employ qualified returning officers",
C: "erode the independence of the institution",
D: "make all parties accept election results",
answer: "C. erode the independence of the institution",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. A person who is denied the right to vote is described as __________.",
A: "uncivil",
B: "disenfranchised",
C: "civil servant",
D: "non-partisan",
answer: "B. disenfranchised",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. Public corporation is a semi-independent statutory body establishment by ________.",
A: "an Act of Parliament",
B: "a civil service commission",
C: "a private sector initiative",
D: "free zones board",
answer: "A. An Act of Parliament",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. One of the objectives of the United Nations Organization (UNO) is to ________.",
A: "establish a standing army",
B: "give loans to poor countries in the world",
C: "promote and encourage respect for human rights and freedoms",
D: "ensure African leaders are respected",
answer: "C. promote and encourage respect for human rights and freedoms",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. The West African Youth League (W.A.Y.L) was a nationalist movement founded by _________.",
A: "Bankole-Bright",
B: "I.T.A. Wallace-Johnson",
C: "J.E. Casely Hayford",
D: "Samuel Akinsanya",
answer: "B. I.T.A. Wallace-Johnson",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. Commonwealth member states derive the following benefits from the association except ___________.",
A: "assistance to war-torn countries",
B: "promotion of education",
C: "political instability",
D: "promotion of sports",
answer: "C. political instability",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. The Economic Community of West African States (ECOWAS) is saddled with many problems, one of which is ________.",
A: "colonial heritage",
B: "facilitation of movement of people",
C: "inter-state trading",
D: "sports and cultural exchange",
answer: "A. colonial heritage",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. In which system of government are all the component units sovereign?",
A: "Confederal",
B: "Federal",
C: "Monarchical",
D: "Republican",
answer: "A. Confederal",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},


]